<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../verbatim_theme/verbatim.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/dev/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/dev/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="lat">De venereis (ap. Oribasium)</title>
                <author xml:lang="lat">
<name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44299175">Galenus</name>
</author>
                <editor xml:lang="lat">Raeder, Ioannes</editor>
                <sponsor>Harvard College Library</sponsor>
                <funder>Harvard Library Arcadia Fund</funder>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="DDD">Digital Divide Data</persName>
                    <resp>Corrected and encoded the text</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
                    <resp>Editor-in-Chief, Perseus Digital Library</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Matt Munson</persName>
                    <resp>Project Manager (University of Leipzig)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Annette Gessner</persName>
                    <resp>Project Assistant (University of Leipzig)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Thibault Clérice</persName>
                    <resp>Lead Developer (University of Leipzig)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Bruce Robertson</persName>
                    <resp>Technical Advisor</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
<editionStmt resp="#Galenus_verbatim">
<edition n="1">Revised edition of the originally published versions of the electronic texts.
<date type="revision" when="2024">2024</date>
</edition>
<respStmt>
<resp>To reuse the Kühn’s edition for the Galenus verbatim project, we corrected the texts as found in the <orgName source="https://github.com/OpenGreekAndLatin/First1KGreek">First1KGreek</orgName> repository, whether there were mistakes of transcriptions, errors in the metadata or missing parts of the text. We added bibliographical references to the previous editions referred to in Kühn’s edition as "Bas." and "Chart.": that of the Γαληνοῦ Ἅπαντα published in Basel (hence referred to as #Basel) and the Operum Hippocratis Coi, et Galeni Pergameni of René Chartier (hence referred to as #Chartier); we changed the naming schemes of the milestones indicating the corresponding Basel and Chartier pages in Kühn’s edition, and added the corresponding Basel and Chartier volume number. The editions other than that of Kühn were given milestones indicating the corresponding Kühn volume and pages when they were missing. Treatises from Kühn’s edition were given line numbers. We also added elements of structuration that were present in Kühn’s edition but were missing in the TEI, mainly the division of chapters into sections in some treatises, as well as the header for those sections. The text of headings containing the name of chapter and numbers of chapters and sections have been restored, as well as the original symbols as they appear within the printed text of Kühn’s edition. The text numbered tlg0057.tlg096 that was separately edited was reinserted in the tlg0057.tlg095 in accordance with its location within Kühn’s edition. For details, see the revisionDesc section.</resp>
<orgName xml:id="Galenus_verbatim" ref="https://galenus-verbatim.huma-num.fr/">Galenus verbatim, funded by the Institut universitaire de France and the Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</orgName>
<persName>Nathalie Rousseau, Sorbonne Université</persName>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor-in-Chief, Galenus verbatim</resp>
<orgName ref="#Galenus_verbatim">Galenus verbatim, funded by the Institut universitaire de France and the Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</orgName>
<persName>Nathalie Rousseau, Sorbonne Université</persName>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Lead Developer, Optéos</resp>
<persName>Frédéric Glorieux</persName>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp from="2021-11" to="2023-03">Digital Editor, Galenus verbatim</resp>
<orgName ref="#Galenus_verbatim">Galenus verbatim, funded by the Institut universitaire de France and the Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</orgName>
<persName>Cahal Taaffe</persName>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp from="2024-02-19" to="2024-07-19">Digital Editor, Galenus verbatim</resp>
<persName>Lucas Lemperriere, Université de Rouen</persName>
<orgName ref="#Galenus_verbatim">Galenus verbatim, funded by the Institut universitaire de France and the Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</orgName>
</respStmt>
<funder ref="https://www.iufrance.fr/">Institut universitaire de France</funder>
<funder ref="https://www.sorbonne-universite.fr/">Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</funder>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
                <authority>Harvard College Library</authority>
                <idno type="filename">tlg0057.tlg035.1st1K-grc3.xml</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International
                        License</licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2016</date>
                <publisher>Harvard College Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title xml:lang="lat">Oribasii collectionum medicarum reliquiae</title>
                            <editor>
                                <persName>
                                    <name xml:lang="lat">Raeder, Ioannes</name>
                                    <name>Raeder, Hans</name>
                                </persName>
                            </editor>
                            <author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0057">Galen</author>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher xml:lang="lat">B.G. Teubneri</publisher>
                                <pubPlace xml:lang="lat">Leipzig et Berolini</pubPlace>
                                <date>1928</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope unit="pp" from="187" to="189">187-189</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                        <ref target="http://cmg.bbaw.de/epubl/online/cmg_06_01_01.php">Corpus
                            Medicorum Graecorum/Latinorum</ref>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards (January 2014)</p>
              <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="(.+)" n="chapter" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
            </refsDecl>
<editorialDecl resp="#Galenus_verbatim">
<correction>
<p>Typographical errors are marked up by a &lt;choice&gt; element.</p>
</correction>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>End-of-line hyphenation is silently removed where appropriate.</p>
</hyphenation>
<interpretation>
<p>The layout of the original edition is marked up by &lt;pb&gt; and &lt;lb&gt; elements. The indentation type has been systematically specified with a rend value.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Titles for books of treatises are marked up by a &lt;head&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Divisions in works, books, chapters, sections are marked up by a &lt;div&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Headings are marked up by a &lt;label&gt; element. Greek numbers in headings of chapters or sections are marked up by a &lt;num&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Verse lines are marked up by an &lt;l&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Linegroups are marked up by an &lt;lg&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Tables are marked up by a &lt;table&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>In the commentaries, Hippocratic lemmas are marked up by a &lt;quote&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<normalization>
<p>Original symbols are maintained as they appear within the printed text of Kühn’s edition.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
                
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">First round of revisions for publication on the Galenus verbatim website.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Added bibliographical information on the editions referred to in Kühn’s edition as "Bas." and "Chart."</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Corrected and added milestone tags for the missing page changes of both Basel and Chartier editions when they were missing.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Punctual correction to the digitization of Kühn’s text.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Correction and additions of the sections &lt;div&gt; level when they were missing to better reflect the structure of Kühn’s edition.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Modification to the subtype of some &lt;div&gt; to better reflect Kühn’s structure.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Added &lt;label&gt; elements for all headings of chapters and sections.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Added &lt;l&gt; elements for verse lines and &lt;lg&gt; elements for linegroups.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Replaced abbreviations introduced by the initial transcription by the original symbols as they appear within the printed text of Kühn’s edition.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Added line number.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2024">The text of headings containing the name of chapter and numbers of chapters and sections have been restored and marked with &lt;label&gt; and &lt;num&gt; elements.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2024">All the indentations have been restored.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="grc" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0057.tlg035.1st1K-grc3">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1" xml:id="_1">
                    <pb n="187"/>
                    <lb n="5"/>
                    <head>λε. Περὶ τῆϲ ἐπὶ τῶν ϲιμῶν διαβάϲεωϲ, ἐκ τοῦ αὐτοῦ λόγου.</head>
                    <lb n="534"/>
                    <p>Πνεύματοϲ τονωτικὸν τοῦτο τὸ γυμνάϲιον καὶ εὐκαμπείαϲ τῆϲ <lb n="1"/> περὶ τὸ
                        ϲῶμα, μάλιϲτα δὲ τῆϲ περὶ ϲκέλη ποιητικὸν μετὰ τοῦ καὶ ἰϲχὺν περιποιεῖν τοῖϲ
                        κινουμένοιϲ μέρεϲιν· ἔϲτι δὲ καὶ μακροτονίαϲ παραϲκευαϲτικὸν καὶ νεύρων
                        καταλλάξεωϲ ἐπιτρεπτικόν· μεταβιβάζει <lb n="10"/> καὶ ὕλην καὶ περιττώματα
                        μετέωρα πρὸϲ τὰϲ ἐξόδουϲ ἀπωθεῖ. εἰ δὲ <lb n="2"/> καὶ μετὰ κρατήϲεωϲ
                        ἁλτηρίων παραλαμβάνοιτο, τῶν ϲτιβαρωτάτων γυμναϲίων ἕν τι γίνεται, διαπονοῦν
                        ὁμοίωϲ καὶ τὰ ἄνω καὶ τὰ κάτω τοῦ ϲώματοϲ.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2" xml:id="_2">
                    <head>λϛ. Περὶ ὁπλομαχίαϲ, ἐκ τοῦ αὐτοῦ λόγου.</head>
                    <lb n="15"/>
                    <p>Οὐ τῶν παλαιῶν γυμναϲίων τοῦτο, λέγω δὲ τῶν τοῖϲ κά|μνουϲιν <lb n="1"/><lb n="535"/> ὠφελίμων, ἐπεὶ ἄλλωϲ ἡ ἐν ὅπλοιϲ ἄϲκηϲιϲ παλαιά. Ῥωμαῖοι δ᾿
                        ἐξεῦρον <lb n="2"/> τὴν ὁπλομαχίαν τήνδε, πρῶτον δ᾿ ὑπὲρ τῆϲ εἰϲ πόλεμον
                        παραϲκευῆϲ· τὸ δὲ νῦν ὑπὲρ τοῦ διαπονεῖν τὰ ϲώματα οἵ γε οὖν ϲτρατιῶται·
                        μονομάχων γὰρ ὅπλα ἐνδυόμενοι ἢ πρὸϲ ἀντιπάλουϲ ἢ πρὸϲ <lb n="20"/> κίονα ὡϲ
                        πρὸϲ ἀντίπαλον διαμάχονται. δύναται δὲ τοῦτο τὸ γυμνάϲιον <lb n="3"/>
                        εὐκίνητόν τε ποιῆϲαι τὸ ϲῶμα καὶ εὔϲαρκον· πλαδαρὰν μέντοι ϲάρκα περιποιεῖ·
                        κεφαλῇ δ᾿ ἀλυϲιτελὲϲ διά τε τὸ ϲκέπεϲθαι λίαν αὐτὴν ὑπὸ τῶν πίλων καὶ τῆϲ
                        περικεφαλαίαϲ διά τε τὸ μοχθεῖν ὑπὸ τοῦ βάρουϲ. μέγιϲτον δ᾿ ἐπάγγελμα τοῦδε
                        τοῦ γυμναϲίου μακρόπνοια καὶ<lb n="4"/>
                        <lb n="25"/> ϲυντονία τοῦ ϲώματοϲ, ἔνθεν οἱ προεθίϲαντεϲ αὐτῷ πᾶϲαν ἄλλην
                        ἀποδίωξιν πνεύματοϲ ὑποφέρειν εἰϲὶν ἱκανοί. |</p>
                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3" xml:id="_3">
                    <head>λζ. Περὶ ἀφροδιϲίων, ἐκ τῶν Γαληνοῦ.</head>
                    <lb n="536"/>
                    <p>Ἀφροδιϲίων δὲ κατὰ μὲν Ἐπίκουρον οὐδεμία χρῆϲιϲ ὑγιεινή· κατὰ <lb n="1"/> δὲ
                        τἀληθὲϲ ἐκ διαλειμμάτων τηλικούτων, ὡϲ ἐπὶ ταῖϲ χρήϲεϲι μήτε <lb n="30"/>
                        ἐκλύϲεωϲ αἰϲθάνεϲθαι καὶ κουφότερον αὐτὸν αὑτοῦ δοκεῖν γεγονέναι καὶ
                        εὐπνούϲτερον. ὁ δὲ καιρὸϲ τῆϲ χρήϲεωϲ, ὅταν ἀκριβῶϲ μέϲον ᾖ <lb n="2"/> τῶν
                        ἔξωθεν περιϲτάϲεων ἁπαϲῶν τὸ ϲῶμα, μήτε ὑπερπεπληρωμένον <note type="footnote">28 — p. 188, 5 Gal. Art. med. 24 (I 371—372 K.) 28 cf.
                            Epicur. fragm. 62 Usener</note>
                        <note type="footnote">2 ελοκρατυντικὸν codd.: corr. Matthaei νεύρα A1
                            τριπτὸν A1 5 x inscriptione solum praebet περὶ τῆ A1 7 τῆϲ] τοῖϲ N 9
                            ἐπιϲτρεπτικόν N 10 ἀποδεῖ C 11 ἀρτηριῶν codd.: corr. C2Dg 14
                            inscriptionen om. A1 16 ἐπεὶ δ᾿ ἄλλωϲ C 18 διποιεῖν A 20 διαμάχονταϲ C
                            21 ἀκίνητον C 22 τὸ] τοῦ CN ϲκέπτεϲθαι codd.: corr. N1 Matthaei 25 ἔνθα
                            codd.: corr Dg προενθίϲαντεϲ codd: corr. C2N2Dg 25. 26 ἀποδίωϲιν C 27
                            nscriptionem om. A1 ἐκ τῶν om. A2C: ἐκ τοῦ N 29 μήτε] μετ᾿ C</note>
                        <note type="footnote">31 εὐνούϲτερον N1: ἀπλούϲτερον C 32 περιϲτάϲεων om, C
                            μήτε] μεθ’ C ὑπερπληρωμένον N</note>
                        <pb n="188"/> μήτε ἐνδεὲϲ μήτε ὑπερεψυγμένον μήτε ὑπερτεθερμαϲμένον <add cause="fix">ἢ ἐξηραμ <lb n="3"/> μένον ἢ ὑγραϲμένον</add> ἀμέτρωϲ. εἰ δὲ
                        καὶ διαμαρτάνοιέν ποτε κατά τι, μικρὸν μὲν ἔϲτω τὸ ἁμαρτανόμενον· ἄμεινον δὲ
                        τὸ τεθερμαϲμένῳ <lb n="537"/> μᾶλλον ἢ ἐψυγμένῳ, | καὶ πεπληρωμένῳ μᾶλλον ἢ
                            <add cause="fix">ἐνδεεῖ, καὶ ὑγραϲμένῳ μᾶλλον ἢ</add> ἐξηραμμένῳ τῷ
                        ϲώματι χρῆϲθαι τοῖϲ ἀφροδιϲίοιϲ. <lb n="5"/>
                        <lb n="4"/> οἱ μὲν οὖν ἀϲθενῆ τὴν δύναμιν ἔχοντεϲ ὑπὸ τῆϲ λαγνείαϲ εἰϲ
                        ἐϲχάτην ἀρρωϲτίαν ἀφικνοῦνται· οἱ δ’ ἰϲχυρὰν καὶ νοϲοῦντεϲ ἀπὸ φλέγματοϲ
                            <add cause="fix">οὔτε καταλυθήϲονται καὶ ξηραίνουϲι τὴν τοῦ
                            φλεγματοϲ</add> περιουϲίαν τῷ διαφορεῖν ἐπὶ πλέον τοὺϲ χυμούϲ· ἀβλαβῆ
                        γὰρ ἀφροδίϲια τοῖϲ <lb n="5"/> ὑγροῖϲ καὶ θερμοῖϲ ἐϲτι καὶ ὅϲοι φύϲει
                        πολύϲπερμοι. ἀλλὰ καὶ θερμαίνει <lb n="10"/> τὸ ϲῶμα τοῖϲ ἐρρωμένην ἔχουϲι
                        τὴν δύναμιν ἡ λαγνεία· τοῖϲ δ᾿ ἀϲθενέϲιν ἐν μὲν τῷ παραχρῆμα θερμαίνει.
                        ψύχει δὲ μετὰ ταῦτω <lb n="538"/><lb n="6"/> γενναίωϲ. ἔνιοι μὲν οὖν εὐ|θέωϲ
                        ἐπὶ ταῖϲ ϲυνουϲίαιϲ ἀπὸ νεότητοϲ ἀϲθενεῖϲ γίνονται· τινὲϲ δέ, εἰ μὴ ϲυνεχῶϲ
                        χρῷντο, βαρύνονται τὴν κεφαλὴν ἀϲώδειϲ τε καὶ πυρετώδειϲ γίνονται καὶ χεῖρον
                        ὀρέγονται <lb n="15"/> καὶ ἧττον πέττουϲιν· τοιαύτηϲ γοῦν ἐνίουϲ ὄνταϲ
                        φύϲεωϲ, εἶτα ἐγκρατεῖϲ ἀφροδιϲίων χρήϲεωϲ γενομένουϲ ναρκώδειϲ τε καὶ
                        δυϲκινήτουϲ ἔγνωμεν ἀποτελεϲθένταϲ, ἐνίουϲ δὲ καὶ ϲκυθρωπούϲ ἀλόγωϲ καὶ
                        δυϲέλπιδαϲ ὁμοίωϲ τοῖϲ μελαγχολικοῖϲ, ταῦτα δὲ παυόμενα ταχέωϲ ἐπὶ ταῖϲ <lb n="7"/> τῶν ἀφροδιϲίων χρήϲεϲιν. ταῦτα ἀναλογιζομένῳ μοι μεγάλωϲ
                        φαίνεται <lb n="20"/> βλάπτειν ἡ τοῦ ϲπέρματοϲ ἐπίϲχεϲιϲ, ἐφ᾿ ὧν αὐτό τε
                        φύϲει κακοχυμότερον καὶ πλεῖον, ἀργότερόϲ τε ὁ βίοϲ, καὶ τῶν ἀφροδιϲίων ἡ
                            <lb n="539"/> χρῆϲιϲ πρότερον μὲν ἱκανὴ πάνυ, μετὰ ταῦτα δὲ <gap reason="omitted"/> | ἰϲχυροί τε καὶ νέοι· τούτοιϲ ἡ τοῦ ϲώματοϲ ἕξιϲ εἰϲ
                        ἀραιότητα πλέον ἤπερ ἡ δύναμιϲ εἰϲ ἀρρωϲτίαν ἀλλοιοῦται, καὶ τοίνυν
                        ἐπανόρθωϲιϲ διὰ τῶν <lb n="25"/> ϲυναγόντων καὶ ϲφιγγόντων γίνεται αὐτοῖϲ,
                        ὁποῖόν ἐϲτι τὸ παραϲκευαϲτικὸν <lb n="8"/> γυμνάϲιον. εἰ δὲ δὴ καὶ ψῦξίϲ τιϲ
                        ἐπὶ τοῖϲ ἀφροδιϲίοιϲ ἐγγίνοιτο, καὶ κατὰ τοῦτο ἂν εἴη τῷ παραϲκευαϲτικῷ
                        γυμναϲίῳ χρηϲτέον· <lb n="9"/> ἐπεγείρει γὰρ τὴν θερμότητα. τῆϲ δ᾿ ὥραϲ τοῦ
                        ἔτουϲ ἐπιτρεπούϲηϲ, <lb n="10"/> οὐδὲ τῆϲ ψυχρολουϲίαϲ ἀφεκτέον. ἐδέϲματα δὲ
                        τῷ πλήθει μὲν ἐλάττω, <lb n="30"/> τῇ ποιότητι δ᾿ ὑγρότερα δοτέον, ἵνα καὶ
                        πέψη καλῶϲ αὐτὰ καὶ τὴν <lb n="11"/> ἐκ τῶν ἀφροδιϲίων ἐπανορθώϲηται
                        ξηρότητα. χρὴ δ᾿ οὐδὲ ψυχρότερα τὴν κρᾶϲιν, ἀλλὰ τῆϲ μέϲηϲ ἰδέαϲ τῶν
                        θερμαινόντων ὑπάρχειν αὐτὰ· <note type="footnote">6—9 Gal. in Hipp. Epid. VI
                            comm. V 23 (XVIII 2, 284 K.) 9—10 Gal. De san. tu. VI 4, 5 (VI 402 K.)
                            10—13 Gal. in Hipp. Epid. VI comm. V 23 (XVII 2, 384 K.) 13—23 Gal. De
                            loc. aff. VI 5 (VIII 417—419 K.) 23—p. 189, 4 Gal. De san. tu. III 11,
                            9—15 (VI 223—224 K.)</note>
                        <note type="footnote">1 ήτε (primo loco)] μετ᾿ C μήτε secundum om. C μήτε
                            ὑπερτεθερμαϲμένον om. C 1. 2 ἢ ἐξηραμμένον ἢ ὑγραϲμένον add. N2Dg e Gal.
                            3 ὸ διαμαρτανόμενον Ϲ τὸ (posteriore loco) Dg: τῷ codd. 4 ἢ posterius
                            om. AC 4. 5 suppl. Dg 6 post ὑπὸ add. τε C 8 suppl. Dg e Gal. περιουϲίαϲ
                            9 ἀβλαβὴϲ codd.: corr. C2Dg 11 ἀρρωμένην C 12 δ᾿ om. C</note>
                        <note type="footnote">τῷ om. 4 13 εὐθέωϲ] θέωϲ A 15 ἀϲώδειϲ] νοϲώδειϲ A 17
                            ἀφροδηϲίαϲ C 20 μοι] μὴ C 21 ἐπίχυϲιϲ codd.: corr. C2Dg 23 lacunam
                            indicavi</note>
                        <note type="footnote">τε om. C 24 ἀριθμότητα codd.: corr. Dg 26 ϲυναγαγόντων
                            A. 29 τοῦ ἔθουϲ C: τούτουϲ A1 30 δὲ om. Ϲ 31 ὑγρότερον codd.: corr.
                            C2N2Dg 32 ψυχροτέραν N: ψυχροτέραν C: χυχροτέραν A</note>
                        <pb n="189"/> διότι γὰρ | ἐξ ἀφροδιϲίων ἀραιότερον ἅμα καὶ ἀϲθενέϲτερον καὶ
                        ξηρότερον <lb n="540"/> ἀποτελεῖται τὸ ϲῶμα, χρὴ δήπου τὰ πυκνοῦντα καὶ
                        θερμαίνοντα καὶ τὴν δύναμιν ἀναρρωννύντα προϲφέρεϲθαι, καὶ τούτουϲ εἶναι
                        ϲκοποὺϲ ἐπ᾿ αὐτοῖϲ.</p>
                </div>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
