<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../verbatim_theme/verbatim.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/dev/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/dev/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="lat">De bono habitu</title>
        <author xml:lang="lat">
<name ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44299175">Galenus</name>
</author>
        <editor role="editor">Kühn, Karl Gottlob</editor>
        <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Published original versions of the electronic texts</resp>
          <orgName ref="http://www.graeco-arabic-studies.org/">A Digital Corpus for Graeco-Arabic Studies, funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</orgName>
          <persName>Mark Schiefsky, Harvard University</persName>
          <persName>Gregory R. Crane, Universität Leipzig</persName>
          <persName>Uwe Vagelpohl, University of Warwick</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Keyboarding</resp>
          <orgName xml:id="DDD">Digital Divide Data</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor-in-Chief, Perseus Digital Library</resp>
          <persName>Gregory R. Crane</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Project Manager (University of Leipzig)</resp>
          <persName>Matt Munson</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Project Assistant (University of Leipzig)</resp>
          <persName>Annette Geßner</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Lead Developer (University of Leipzig)</resp>
          <persName>Thibault Clérice</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Advisor</resp>
          <persName>Bruce Robertson</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
<editionStmt resp="#Galenus_verbatim">
<edition n="1">Revised edition of the originally published versions of the electronic texts.
<date type="revision" when="2024">2024</date>
</edition>
<respStmt>
<resp>To reuse the Kühn's edition for the Galenus verbatim project, we corrected the texts as found in the <orgName source="https://github.com/OpenGreekAndLatin/First1KGreek">First1KGreek</orgName> repository, whether there were mistakes of transcriptions, errors in the metadata or missing parts of the text. We added bibliographical references to the previous editions referred to in Kühn's edition as "Bas." and "Chart.": that of the Γαληνοῦ Ἅπαντα published in Basel (hence referred to as #Basel) and the Operum Hippocratis Coi, et Galeni Pergameni of René Chartier (hence referred to as #Chartier); we changed the naming schemes of the milestones indicating the corresponding Basel and Chartier pages in Kühn's edition, and added the corresponding Basel and Chartier volume number. The editions other than that of Kühn were given milestones indicating the corresponding Kühn volume and pages when they were missing. Treatises from Kühn's edition were given line numbers. We also added elements of structuration that were present in Kühn's edition but were missing in the TEI, mainly the division of chapters into sections in some treatises, as well as the header for those sections. The text of headings containing the name of chapter and numbers of chapters and sections have been restored, as well as the original symbols as they appear within the printed text of Kühn's edition. The text numbered tlg0057.tlg096 that was separately edited was reinserted in the tlg0057.tlg095 in accordance with its location within Kühn's edition. For details, see the revisionDesc section.</resp>
<orgName xml:id="Galenus_verbatim" ref="https://galenus-verbatim.huma-num.fr/">Galenus verbatim, funded by the Institut universitaire de France and the Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</orgName>
<persName>Nathalie Rousseau, Sorbonne Université</persName>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor-in-Chief, Galenus verbatim</resp>
<orgName ref="#Galenus_verbatim">Galenus verbatim, funded by the Institut universitaire de France and the Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</orgName>
<persName>Nathalie Rousseau, Sorbonne Université</persName>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Lead Developer, Optéos</resp>
<persName>Frédéric Glorieux</persName>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp from="2021-11" to="2023-03">Digital Editor, Galenus verbatim</resp>
<orgName ref="#Galenus_verbatim">Galenus verbatim, funded by the Institut universitaire de France and the Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</orgName>
<persName>Cahal Taaffe</persName>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp from="2024-02-19" to="2024-07-19">Digital Editor, Galenus verbatim</resp>
<persName>Lucas Lemperriere, Université de Rouen</persName>
<orgName ref="#Galenus_verbatim">Galenus verbatim, funded by the Institut universitaire de France and the Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</orgName>
</respStmt>
<funder ref="https://www.iufrance.fr/">Institut universitaire de France</funder>
<funder ref="https://www.sorbonne-universite.fr/">Initiative humanités biomédicales de l’Alliance Sorbonne Université</funder>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
        <authority>A Digital Corpus for Graeco-Arabic Studies, funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</authority>
        <publisher>University of Leipzig</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Germany</pubPlace>
        <idno type="filename">tlg0057.tlg025.1st1K-grc1.xml</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
        </availability>
        <date>2016</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title xml:lang="lat">Claudii Galeni Opera Omnia</title>
            <author xml:lang="lat">Galenus</author>
            <editor role="editor">Kühn, Karl Gottlob</editor>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cnobloch</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Leipzig</pubPlace>
              <biblScope unit="vol">4</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="pp" from="750" to="756">750-756</biblScope>
              <date>1822</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/chi.11102513">HathiTrust</ref>
        </biblStruct>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr corresp="Basel">
            <title xml:lang="lat">Γαληνοῦ Ἅπαντα. Galeni Pergameni Opera omnia</title>
            <author xml:lang="lat">Galenus</author>
            <editor>Camerarius, Joachim</editor>
            <editor>Fuchs, Leonhart</editor>
            <editor>Gemusaeus, Hieronymus</editor>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cratander</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Basel</pubPlace>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="pp" from="248" to="249">248-249</biblScope>
              <date>1538</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <ref target="https://www.biusante.parisdescartes.fr/histmed/medica/cote?00039x01">BIU Santé, Medica</ref>
        </biblStruct>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr corresp="Chartier">
            <title xml:lang="lat">Magni Hippocratis Coi, et Claudii Galeni Pergameni archiatrΩn uniuersa quae extant</title>
            <author xml:lang="lat">Galenus</author>
            <editor>Chartier, René</editor>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>[s.n.]</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
              <biblScope unit="vol">6</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="pp" from="6" to="7">6-7</biblScope>
              <date>1638</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <ref target="https://www.biusante.parisdescartes.fr/histmed/medica/cote?00013x06">BIU Santé, Medica</ref>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture.</p>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(.+)" n="work" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
<editorialDecl resp="#Galenus_verbatim">
<correction>
<p>Typographical errors are marked up by a &lt;choice&gt; element.</p>
</correction>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>End-of-line hyphenation is silently removed where appropriate.</p>
</hyphenation>
<interpretation>
<p>The layout of the original edition is marked up by &lt;pb&gt; and &lt;lb&gt; elements. The indentation type has been systematically specified with a rend value.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Titles for books of treatises are marked up by a &lt;head&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Divisions in works, books, chapters, sections are marked up by a &lt;div&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Headings are marked up by a &lt;label&gt; element. Greek numbers in headings of chapters or sections are marked up by a &lt;num&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Verse lines are marked up by an &lt;l&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Linegroups are marked up by an &lt;lg&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>Tables are marked up by a &lt;table&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<interpretation>
<p>In the commentaries, Hippocratic lemmas are marked up by a &lt;quote&gt; element.</p>
</interpretation>
<normalization>
<p>Original symbols are maintained as they appear within the printed text of Kühn's edition.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
        
        
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">First round of revisions for publication on the Galenus verbatim website.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Added bibliographical information on the editions referred to in Kühn's edition as "Bas." and "Chart."</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Corrected and added milestone tags for the missing page changes of both Basel and Chartier editions when they were missing.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Punctual correction to the digitization of Kühn's text.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Correction and additions of the sections &lt;div&gt; level when they were missing to better reflect the structure of Kühn's edition.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Modification to the subtype of some &lt;div&gt; to better reflect Kühn's structure.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Added &lt;label&gt; elements for all headings of chapters and sections.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Added &lt;l&gt; elements for verse lines and &lt;lg&gt; elements for linegroups.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Replaced abbreviations introduced by the initial transcription by the original symbols as they appear within the printed text of Kühn's edition.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2023">Added line number.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2024">The text of headings containing the name of chapter and numbers of chapters and sections have been restored and marked with &lt;label&gt; and &lt;num&gt; elements.</change>
<change who="#Galenus_verbatim" when="2024">All the indentations have been restored.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="edition" xml:lang="grc" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0057.tlg025.1st1K-grc1">
        <pb n="4.750"/>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="work" n="1" xml:id="_1">
          <head>ΓΑΛΗΝΟΥ ΠΕΡΙ ΕΥΕΞΙΑΣ
<lb/>ΒΙΒΛΙΟΝ.
</head>
          <p rend="indent">
<lb n="1"/>Τὸ τῆς ἕξεως ὄνομα κατὰ παντὸς ἐπιφέρειν εἰθίσμεθα
<lb n="2"/>τοῦ μονίμου τε καὶ δυσλύτου, καὶ οὐδὲν μᾶλλον ἐπαινοῦντες,
<lb n="3"/>ἢ ψέγοντες. ἀλλ’ ὅταν εὐεξίαν ἢ καχεξίαν εἴπωμεν,
<lb n="4"/>ἤδη τηνικαῦτα διορίζομεν, ὁποίαν τινὰ τὴν ἕξιν εἶναί
<lb n="5"/>φαμεν. ἀγαθὴ μὲν οὖν ἁπλῶς ἕξις ἐν ἀρίστῃ κατασκευῇ
<lb n="6"/>γίνεται σώματος, οὐχ ἁπλῶς δὲ καὶ καθ’ ἑκάστην φύσιν
<lb n="7"/>σώματος. ἡ μέντοι καχεξία περὶ πᾶσαν συνίσταται κατασκευὴν
<pb n="4.751"/>
<lb n="1"/>σώματος, εἴθ’ ἁπλῶς, εἴτ’ ἐν τῷ πρός τι λέγοιτο.
<lb n="2"/>χρὴ τοίνυν ἀναμνησθῆναι τῶν περὶ ἀρίστης κατασκευῆς
<lb n="3"/>εἰρημένων ἰδίᾳ τὸν βουλόμενον ἀκριβῶς ἐπιγνῶναι, τί
<lb n="4"/>ποτέ ἐστιν ἁπλῶς εἰπεῖν εὐεξία. πλάτος γὰρ ἱκανὸν ἐχούσης
<lb n="5"/>τῆς ὑγείας, ὡς πολλάκις ἐν ἑτέροις ἐπιδέδεικται, τὴν
<lb n="6"/>μὲν ἐπίτασιν αὐτῆς εὐεξίαν ὀνομάζουσιν οἱ παλαιοὶ φιλόσοφοί
<lb n="7"/>τε καὶ ἰατροὶ, τὴν δὲ ἔκλυσιν ἰδίῳ μὲν οὐκέτι
<lb n="8"/>προσαγορεύουσιν ὀνόματι, τὸ δὲ τοῦ παντὸς γένους ὡσαύτως
<lb n="9"/>ὑγείαν <milestone unit="ed1page" n="1.249"/>καλοῦντες. ὥστ’ ἀρίστη τις ὑγεία ἡ
<lb n="10"/>εὐεξία, καὶ διὰ τοῦτο ἐν τοῖς ἄριστα κατεσκευασμένοις γίνεται
<lb n="11"/>σώμασιν. εἰ γάρ τι μὴ τοιοῦτον, οὐκ ἂν δέξαιτο τὴν
<lb n="12"/>ἀρίστην ὑγείαν, ὥστ’ οὐδὲ τὴν εὐεξίαν. εἰ δὲ ἐν τῷ πρός
<lb n="13"/>τι, κατὰ τὴν ἑκάστου φύσιν γίνεται, καὶ διὰ τοῦτο μετὰ
<lb n="14"/>προσθήκης λέγεται Δίωνος, εἰ οὕτως ἔτυχεν, ἢ Μίλωνος
<lb n="15"/>εὐεξία, οὐχ ἁπλῶς εὐεξία. ἡ μέν γε τοῦ Μίλωνος, καὶ
<lb n="16"/>ἡ τοῦ Ἡρακλέους, καὶ ἡ τοῦ Ἀχιλλέως ἁπλῶς τ’ εἰσὶν
<lb n="17"/>εὐεξίαι καὶ χωρὶς προσθήκης ὀνομάζονται, καθάπερ καὶ
<pb n="4.752"/>
<lb n="1"/>καλὸς μὲν ὁ Ἀχιλλεὺς ἁπλῶς, ὁ δὲ πίθηκος οὐχ ἁπλῶς,
<lb n="2"/>ἀλλ’ ὡς πίθηκος καλός. ἐκ τῶν μετὰ προσθήκης ἐστὶ λεγομένων
<lb n="3"/>καὶ ἡ τῶν ἀθλητῶν εὐεξία, καὶ δεόντως ὑπὲρ
<lb n="4"/>αὐτῆς ὁ Ἱπποκράτης ἔλεγεν· Ἐν τοῖσι γυμναστικοῖσιν αἱ
<lb n="5"/>ἐπ’ ἄκρον εὐεξίαι σφαλεραί. οὐ γὰρ δὴ τήν γε ἁπλῶς
<lb n="6"/>ὀνομαζομένην εὐεξίαν, ἐπειδὰν εἰς ἄκρον ἥκῃ, σφαλερὰν
<lb n="7"/>εἶναί φησιν. αὐτὸ γὰρ δὴ τοῦτό ἐστιν αὐτῇ τὸ εἰς ἄκρον
<lb n="8"/>ἥκειν, τὸ πασῶν τοῦ σώματος τῶν διαθέσεων ὑπάρχειν ἡ
<lb n="9"/>ἀσφαλεστάτη. ἀλλ’ ἡ τῶν ἀθλητῶν, ἢ τῶν γυμναστικῶν,
<lb n="10"/>ἢ ὅπως ἂν ἐθέλοι τις ὀνομάζειν εὐεξίαν, διότι μὴ ἁπλῶς
<lb n="11"/>ἐστιν εὐεξία ἡ ἀρίστη διάθεσις σώματος, <milestone unit="ed2page" n="6.7"/>εὐλόγως εἰς
<lb n="12"/>ἄκρον ἰοῦσα σφαλερωτάτη γίνεται. διάθεσις γὰρ, φησὶν,
<lb n="13"/>ἀθλητικὴ οὐ φύσει, ἕξις ὑγιεινὴ κρείσσων. τῆς μὲν οὖν
<lb n="14"/>ὑγιεινῆς ἕξεως ἡ τελειότης εὐεξία ἐστί· τῆς δὲ τῶν ἀθλητῶν
<lb n="15"/>διαθέσεως οὐχ ἁπλῶς, ἀλλὰ μετὰ προσθήκης, ὡς
<lb n="16"/>εὔμορφος πίθηκος, καὶ πῆχυς μέγας, καὶ ἄδικος χοῖνιξ,
<lb n="17"/>καὶ ἀδόκιμος δραχμή. εἴτε γὰρ ὁ πῆχυς μέγας, οὐκέθ’
<pb n="4.753"/>
<lb n="1"/>ἁπλῶς πῆχυς, ἀλλ’ ὅλον τοῦτο μέγας πῆχυς, εἴτε ἡ χοῖνιξ
<lb n="2"/>ἄδικος, οὐκέθ’ ἁπλῶς χοῖνιξ, ἀλλ’ ὅλον τοῦτο χοῖνιξ ἄδικος.
<lb n="3"/>ὡσαύτως δὲ κᾀπὶ τῶν ἄλλων ἁπάντων τὸ χωρὶς τῆς
<lb n="4"/>προσθήκης ἁπλῶς ὀνομαζόμενον οὐ τῆς αὐτῆς ἐστι φύσεως
<lb n="5"/>τῷ μετὰ προσθήκης λεγομένῳ. ἀλλ’ ἐνίοτε τὸ μὲν
<lb n="6"/>ἄκρως ἐπαινετόν ἐστι, τὸ δὲ, εἰ οὕτως ἔτυχεν, ψεκτόν·
<lb n="7"/>ὥσπερ γε καὶ ἡ τῶν ἀθλητῶν εὐεξία τοσοῦτον δὴ τὸ
<lb n="8"/>ἐπαινετὸν ἔχει, ὥστε ψέγεσθαι δεόντως, οὐχ ὑφ’ Ἱπποκράτους
<lb n="9"/>μόνον, ἢ τῶν ἄλλων ἰατρῶν τῶν παλαιῶν, ἀλλὰ
<lb n="10"/>καὶ πρὸς τῶν ἀρίστων φιλοσόφων, ὡς καὶ Πλάτωνος ἐν
<lb n="11"/>τῷ τρίτῳ τῆς Πολιτείας τήν τε ἀχρηστίαν αὐτῆς ἅπασαν
<lb n="12"/>εἰς τὴν κατὰ φύσιν ἐνέργειαν ἐπιδεικνύντος, καὶ ὡς σφαλερὰ
<lb n="13"/>πρὸς ὑγείαν ἐστὶ διεξιόντος. οὐ γὰρ εὐκρασίαν ἁπλῶς
<lb n="14"/>τοῦ σώματος, ἀλλὰ καὶ μέγεθος ὄγκου μεταδιώκοντος, ὃ
<lb n="15"/>χωρὶς ἀμέτρου πληρώσεως οὐκ ἂν γένοιτο, οὕτω καὶ σφαλερὰν
<lb n="16"/>αὐτὴν ἀπεργάζονται, καὶ πρὸς τὰς πολιτικὰς ἐνεργείας
<lb n="17"/>ἄχρηστον. ἵνα τοίνυν τῆς ὄντως εὐεξίας εἰς ἀκριβῆ
<pb n="4.754"/>
<lb n="1"/>γνῶσιν ἀφικώμεθα, παραλαβεῖν αὐτῇ χρὴ τὴν ὁμώνυμον
<lb n="2"/>εὐεξίαν τὴν ἀθλητικὴν, καὶ σκέψασθαι, τί ταὐτὸν ἑκατέραις
<lb n="3"/>ὑπάρχει, τί τε ἐναντίον. ἡ μὲν δὴ τῶν μορίων ἁπάντων
<lb n="4"/>τοῦ σώματος εὐκρασία κοινὸν ἀμφοῖν. οὕτω δὲ καὶ
<lb n="5"/>ἡ τῶν ἐνεργειῶν ἀρετὴ, καὶ εἴπερ ταῦτα, καὶ ἡ εὐχυμία.
<lb n="6"/>ταυτὶ μὲν τὰ κοινά. τὰ δὲ ἐναντία συμμετρία μὲν αἵματός
<lb n="7"/>τε καὶ τοῦ τῶν στερεῶν σωμάτων ὄγκου παντὸς ἐν
<lb n="8"/>ταῖς ὄντως εὐεξίαις, ἀμετρία δὲ τῶν αὐτῶν τούτων καὶ
<lb n="9"/>μάλιστα τοῦ σαρκώδους γένους ἐν ταῖς ἀθλητικαῖς, αἷς ἐξ
<lb n="10"/>ἀνάγκης ἕπεται τὸ σφαλερὸν, ἐπειδὰν εἰς ἄκρον ἀφίκηται.
<lb n="11"/>ὅταν γὰρ ἐσθίωσι μὲν πρὸς ἀνάγκην, πέττῃ δὲ ἡ γαστὴρ
<lb n="12"/>ἐῤῥωμένως, καὶ ἡ ἀνάδοσις γίνηται ἐπὶ τῇ πέψει ῥᾳδίως,
<lb n="13"/>αἱμάτωσίς τε καὶ πρόσθεσις, καὶ πρόσφυσις, καὶ θρέψις
<lb n="14"/>ἕπηται τοῖσδε, κίνδυνος ὑπερπληρωθῆναι τὴν ἕξιν, ὡς
<lb n="15"/>μηκέτ’ εἶναι τῇ φύσει χώραν προσθέσεως, κᾀν τῷδε πληροῦνται
<lb n="16"/>μὲν αἵματος αἱ φλέβες ἀμέτρως, κατασβέννυται
<lb n="17"/>δὲ καὶ πνίγεται τὸ ἔμφυτον θερμὸν, ἀποροῦν τῆς
<pb n="4.755"/>
<lb n="1"/>διαπνοῆς. εἴπερ δὲ ἔτ’ ἀντέχει τοῦτο, ῥήγνυταί τι τῶν
<lb n="2"/>ἐπικαίρων ἀγγείων, ἃ δὴ κατὰ πνεύμονά τε καὶ ἧπαρ καὶ
<lb n="3"/>θώρακα τέτακται. καὶ γὰρ μαλακώτερα τοῖς χιτῶσι τῶν
<lb n="4"/>ἐν τοῖς κώλοις ὑπάρχει ταῦτα, καὶ πρότερον τὴν τροφὴν
<lb n="5"/>δέχεται, καὶ διὰ τὸ πλῆθος τῆς ἐν αὐτοῖς φυσικῆς θερμασίας,
<lb n="6"/>ἔτι τε τῶν ἐνεργειῶν τὸ διηνεκὲς ὅμοιόν τι τῇ
<lb n="7"/>ζέσει πάσχον τὸ αἷμα τοὺς χιτῶνας αὐτῶν ἀναῤῥήγνυσιν,
<lb n="8"/>ὥσπερ ὁ γλεύκινος οἶνος τοὺς πίθους. ταῦτά τε οὖν οὕτω
<lb n="9"/>γίνεται πάντα, ταῖς ἀμέτροις πληρώσεσιν ἐξ ἀνάγκης ἑπόμενα,
<lb n="10"/>καὶ αἱ περὶ αὐτῶν ἀποδείξεις τοῖς φυσικοῖς ἕπονται
<lb n="11"/>λόγοις. ὅτι δὲ σβέννυται τὸ ἔμφυτον θερμὸν, ὑπερπληρωθεισῶν
<lb n="12"/>αἵματος τῶν φλεβῶν, ἐν τοῖς περὶ χρείας ἀναπνοῆς
<lb n="13"/>εἴρηται, ὅτι δ’ αἱ φλέβες ῥήγνυνται, ἐν τοῖς ἀνατομικοῖς.
<lb n="14"/>οὕτω δ’ ἂν καὶ ὁ Ἱπποκράτης φανείη γινώσκων,
<lb n="15"/>οὐ μόνον ἐπειδὰν φῇ, τὴν ἐν τοῖς γυμναστικοῖς ἐπ’ ἄκρον
<lb n="16"/>εὐεξίαν εἶναι σφαλερὰν, ἀλλὰ κᾀπειδὰν ἑτέρωθι γράφῃ.
<lb n="17"/>Τῷ δὲ ἐξαίφνης ἄφωνον γενέσθαι φλεβῶν ἀπολήψιες τὸ
<pb n="4.756"/>
<lb n="1"/>σῶμα λυπέουσι. τὰς γὰρ αἰφνιδίους παραλύσεις τῶν ἐνεργειῶν
<lb n="2"/>ἁπασῶν διὰ μιᾶς ἐπικαιροτάτης ἐδήλωσεν. ἀπολήψεις
<lb n="3"/>δὲ φλεβῶν τὰς ὑπερπληρώσεις εἶπεν, ἐπειδὰν
<lb n="4"/>ἀπορῶσιν εἰς ἀνάψυξιν διαπνοῆς.
</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
